[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host gavin henry and today my
guest is carl wiegers karl wiegers is
principal consultant with process impact
a software development consulting and
training company in portland oregon he
has a phd in organic chemistry which
we'll touch upon later carl is the
author of 13 books including software
development pearls which we're going to
talk about today the thoughtless design
of everyday things software requirements
successful business analysis consulting
and the forensic mystery novel titled
the reconstruction you've delivered
hundreds of training courses webinars
and conference presentations worldwide
carl welcome to software engineering
radio
well hi gavin thanks very much for
having me i'm happy to be with you today
so i'd like to start with a brief
history of your background and software
and then i've broken the show up into
hopefully six blocks of around ten
minutes each so we can dig into various
sections i found good in your book so
we'll see how we get on we'll do our
best so first of all i'd like to address
the fact that your book says
50 years of experience
has that been a volatile 50 years of
change or was there more or less changed
during certain periods what stands out
for you during those 50 amazing years of
career
yeah it's hard for me to believe it's
been that long in fact it was 50 years
when i started writing software
development pearls i first learned a
program in college in 1970 which is now
almost 52 years ago in september
and i did a lot of programming in
different situations there and also in
graduate school in chemistry at the
university of illinois i did a lot of
software development for various reasons
and started out my career at kodak in
rochester new york as a research
scientist and then after a few years i
moved into full-time software
development and what was interesting is
i also became an atari hobbyist remember
atari computers maybe you're too young
for that but i was an atari hobbyist and
i did a huge amount of programming at
home and even wrote the assembly
language tutorial column for a hobby
magazine for two years
and even programmed some commercial
educational games
so i did a lot of different kinds of
things in software i moved from software
development into
software management and then into a more
of a quality engineering and process
improvement kind of role and started my
company process impact in 1997
plus of course like all of us i've got a
lot of experience as a user
and you know a lot has changed in the
last 50 years about software and
software engineering but one thing i
think that's interesting gavin is that
some things really haven't changed as
much as you might think for example
requirements development that's an area
i've done quite a bit of work in that's
not really a technical problem that's a
communication problem or a thinking and
business kind of problem primarily
so a lot of the challenges that people
face with the requirements long ago are
still valid
that leads us nicely on to um the first
section of the show so you mentioned
requirements which is
spot on for where i'm going with the
show so
in lesson four of your book you say a
user-centric approach to requirements
will meet customer needs better than a
feature-centric approach so i think that
is understanding or trying to understand
what they want from something rather
than the features
could you explain that better than me
and take us through that yeah there's
two separate but related concepts here
you know the first is user engagement
okay and i think we all talk about users
but sometimes i don't think we do a good
enough job of understanding who our
users really are
so i think it's important to do some
stakeholder analysis and then identify
your user classes these are classes
being distinct groups of users who have
largely different maybe not completely
orthogonal but largely different needs
and tasks they need to perform with the
system
so we did that for an information system
project i worked on at kodak called the
chemical tracking system
where i was the lead ba for the third
attempt to get this project done the
first two had failed for some reason and
we identified four distinct user
communities with largely different needs
so that's a good start but then you have
to say all right so who do i talk to who
do i get requirements from that i can
trust
and so in other words who's going to be
the literal voice of the customer for
each of these groups
so when i was a kodak we started this
idea clear back in 1985 of having
product champions was the term we used
for key representatives of each of these
user groups
and those were the people that the
business analysts would work with to try
to understand their requirements
and then we get to the second part of
that question about usage centric versus
feature centric
which is to focus on understanding what
users need to do with the system
not just the features they want to have
in built into the system and what we're
doing and this was a really profound
moment you asked earlier gavin about
times of change in the last 50 years and
one of the really profound changes in my
thinking about software engineering
was when i realized first of all that
there are different kinds of
requirements which i classified very
broadly there's business requirements
user requirements and functional or
solution requirements
but then the real insight i had was when
i learned about use cases and i realized
that
if we talk about what people need to do
with the system we learn a lot more than
if we just ask people well what do you
want
and the first time i applied the use
case technique was on that chemical
tracking system which the previous
business analysts had not managed to get
anywhere with
and it worked remarkably well all of the
user representatives we worked with
really found that approach comfortable
and satisfactory and natural when we're
talking about what are the things you
need to do with the system rather than
what the system should do itself so i
really got sold on use cases in this
usage-centric thinking
and does that
fall under
any type of model that is given a name
today
a type of practice or something or is it
encapsulated in requirements
well that's a good question i think the
use case
rubric overall i think is kind of the
overarching theme there and you do hear
people talk about use cases actually in
daily life sometimes now even though i'm
not sure they're using the term exactly
the way we do in software but the same
idea
and the reason i think this is so
important so i'm not sure there's a
general methodology but but if we focus
on that idea of usage-centric
requirements exploration and
usage-centric design it solves a lot of
problems
if you ask the traditional
question during requirements discussions
what do you want or what are your
requirements those are terrible
questions
what they do is they open the door and
maybe you've had this experience you
just start getting this random pile of
information that's really hard to turn
into a set of useful requirements that
leads to a decent solution
and also another thing that happens you
can focus on features so you implement
functionality that doesn't actually let
users do their job
or you can implement functionality that
no one's ever going to use but you work
pretty hard on building that even if
they don't use it so that's pretty
discouraging too
and why do you think this normally goes
wrong even today
well i think it goes wrong if people a
aren't talking to the right
representatives
who can really represent the needs of a
community of users like a particular
user class
it goes wrong if we leave it so
open-ended and just ask people what they
want and they free associate and they
think well it should let me sort this
list this way and
then you miss the gist of what is the
task you're trying to accomplish and one
way that i try to phrase that question
is think in terms of okay so here's an
app you're going to launch the app what
are you trying to accomplish when you
launch a session with the app
you're not launching it to use some
feature you're launching it to get
something done even if it's a game
you're trying to get something done or
if it's a device or it's a software
application you launch it for a reason
so by trying to understand the reasons
people are are using it and what they're
trying to accomplish
then we go a lot more to the right side
of understanding all right well what
functionality do we have to build to let
you do that and are we sure that that
all aligns with our business objectives
so it goes wrong
if you don't take that kind of approach
and i can give you a great example
so i've been a consultant for about 25
years
and one of my consulting clients once
held a big one-day off-site workshop
they had about 60 participants and they
called this a requirements workshop
broke them into
six subgroups and to collect what they
considered to be requirements for a big
product this company was working on it
was a commercial product
so they took all the output from those
six subgroups
and basically stapled it together
literally and verbatim and said well
here's our requirement specification
but it wasn't that's what i call a pile
there were a lot of useful and important
pieces of information in there but it
wasn't structured or organized in any
useful way
everything was stirred together there
was a lot of extraneous information and
ideas and thoughts just all all thrown
in so by just asking people to
brainstorm what they wanted didn't
produce any actionable requirements
knowledge although there was probably a
pony buried in there somewhere but that
form of having the conversation didn't
lend itself to getting the information
you need to say okay what is it we need
to build
if they did take that big pile of
stapled information
and then came back with something weeks
or months later that's your traditional
waterfall with no requirements
engagement at all isn't it
yeah and it's even worse because you
started with a really bad bucket of
water to dump over the waterfall
at the outset so i think what we really
want to try to do besides having the
ongoing customer engagement
rather than just trying to do it once at
the beginning we all know that doesn't
work real well and i think having
ongoing touch points throughout the
project is really important
but by asking the right kinds of
questions
and then taking the information and
organizing it and structuring it in a
way and i find use cases work very well
for that because
my brain is kind of top down
and i think it's better to start with
some broad strokes or some higher
abstraction thinking like well what are
the tasks we're trying to accomplish
and then elaborate the details over time
at the right time
as opposed to collecting this huge pile
of information and then trying to
organize it and sort it out and say well
what do i do with this
in fact i've got a great example of how
i've seen that happen so i've taught
more than 200 courses on requirements to
audiences of all kinds
and one of the things i do in those
courses as i have the students
participate in a practice requirement
solicitation session after i've
described the use case approach i break
the group into four small teams and i
see the same pattern over and over
hundreds of times now
one of those four teams always seems to
grasp the idea of use cases maybe
because someone's worked with them
before and they make great progress in
that one hour practice solicitation
session two of the other groups need a
little coaching on how to get going with
use cases and then they do fine
but the fourth group almost invariably
struggles
because they don't try what i'm trying
to get them to do which is talk about
use cases they start in the traditional
way of asking the people who are
role-playing the users
well what do you want
and as a result just like i did with
that
that consulting client the facilitator
ends up with this list of random bits of
information that are potentially useful
but there's no structure no focus
no relationship to what the users are
going to do with the system and i've
seen this over and over then the team
just sort of sort of stares at the flip
chart that's got these post-it notes all
over it with these thoughts and and
feature ideas
and they don't know what to do next
so after seeing that over and over i
think that's pretty solid pretty well
sells me on the usage-centric thinking
thanks and does that is this something
that you just do once at the start are
you constantly revisiting and
revalidating the
well the phrase you mean on a real
project
yeah yeah well the term that i use that
i think is applicable is progressive
refinement of detail
and so i think of maybe doing a first
cut to say let's identify these use
cases let's take a user group and let's
talk about what are the things the major
things you'd need to do with this system
that's what we did on the chemical
tracking system project
and then we can do a first cut
prioritization and say well which of
those are going to be more common
or heavily used by lots of people and
which ones are going to be more once in
a while or only certain users
and that helps you start thinking very
early about prioritizing your
development approach whether you're
doing it one time through the project or
whether you're doing it in small
increments
and then you can take each of those
based on their priority and start
refining them into further amounts of
detail to get a richer understanding and
yes you do have to revisit that as we go
along because people will think of new
things people will
realize that maybe something someone
suggested is now obsolete in our
business or whatever so i think it has
to be a dynamic ongoing thing
but that's why i use the term
progressive refinement of detail rather
than trying to get that all right away
thank you i'd like to
discuss now what you call design in
lesson 18 you state it's cheaper to
iterate at higher levels of of
abstraction can you take us through
uh abstraction prototyping modeling
designs things like that
sure so when i'm thinking about higher
levels of abstraction you can imagine a
scale where the highest level of
abstraction you've got a concept for a
project
or a product let's say and then as you
move down this abstraction scale a
little bit you start talking about
requirements and and use maybe you start
doing some prototyping or modeling so we
start progressively moving from concept
to something that's more tangible and at
the lowest level of abstraction when
you're building a piece of software you
have code and that's the ultimate
reality of course
but all those things expand as you're
going down that abstraction scale so the
idea behind that lesson that is cheaper
to iterate at higher levels of
abstraction is that it's first of all
it's nearly impossible to get a design
right that is an optimized solution on
your first try at least i can't do it
it usually takes multiple attempts kind
of refining my understanding of both the
problem
and potential solutions on each cycle
so we want to think of how can you
iterate one way is to write the code
over and over trying to get the solution
right and that's iteration at a low
level of abstraction
or you can try to iterate at higher
levels like concepts the requirements
models prototypes
and it takes less work to create each of
those kinds of artifacts on each
iterative pass so than it does doing it
with code so you can iterate more
quickly and more times
and i think that gives you more chances
of getting it right has that been your
experience that it takes more than one
try to get kind of the the solution that
you feel best about
yeah i think
starting off with design first and then
moving into requirements
in a project where
you have the idea that things appear as
you move forward and then you have to
tackle them and i think that fits nicely
with how you say your requirements
constantly change
as you think about and discuss parts of
a project your example was the chemical
software application was that analysis
or what sort of application was it it
was a tracking system so it was
basically a database application where
we could keep track of all the thousands
and thousands of bottles of different
chemicals both in the uh stock loom
inventories throughout this very large
company and also in individual
laboratories so that we could just order
new chemicals maybe try to find a bottle
that's already around somewhere in the
company so you don't have to buy a new
bottle from a vendor disposed safely of
expired chemicals and that sort of thing
so it was a big inventory system
essentially with a lot of tracking of
individual containers that's what it was
about
so in the two lessons that we just spoke
about would the design have come first
or the use case of we want to manage and
track
absolutely the use cases absolutely
start with the use cases because how do
i know what to design until i know what
functionality it has to provide and how
do i know what functionality it has to
provide until i know what people are
trying to accomplish with it but that's
tricky because the way you can phrase a
sentence in english you could
say i need to design a chemical
tracking application couldn't you or you
could say my requirements are a chemical
tracking application yeah so that would
be the super highest level of
abstraction right that's a concept that
doesn't tell you anything about the
solution that tells you about your
business objectives maybe you know and i
think you do really need to start with
an understanding of the business
objectives which is why do we need to
build a chemical tracking system which
comes back to the requirements yeah
right so that's that top level of
requirements or our business objectives
which is really the motivation of why
are we spending money and time on this
instead of on something else what's it
going to do for us what financial
benefit or compliance benefit or
whatever
are we trying to accomplish with that
and that i think then helps you start
identifying your stakeholders start
identifying these user classes and then
i find use cases are just an excellent
way to have the conversation initially
with those users to say all right if we
need this system and one of the big
drivers for it was compliance there were
regulations that said you guys have to
report to the government how you're
disposing of chemicals and storing them
safely and all that that was our major
business driver so not just potential
commercial wastage
no that was kind of a nice side benefit
but the principal driver and the key
customer was the guy who was responsible
for
managing reports to the government for
health and safety purposes of how the
chemicals were being acquired stored and
disposed of in the genesee river i mean
the cafeteria you know wherever they got
rid of them
so yeah if you didn't do the use cases
correctly there you might go down the
feature centric or
the wrong approach where you think
you're trying to save money or you're
trying to find something quickly or find
out when it's expired but that's not the
top level thing you're trying to do that
was an important component of it but it
wasn't the key driver so so that's why i
think you need this sort of stack of
requirements and that was a big eye
opener for me is when i realized ah
there are different kinds of things we
call requirements there are different
kinds of things we call design we need
to put adjectives in front of them
and so even having an understanding then
of the major tasks people need to
accomplish with this that will hopefully
achieve our business objectives
you still need to design the software
the architecture the detailed design the
database design the user experience
design and i found prototypes were a
very good way to help with that
iteration it's a what helps bring
clarity to the problem to the
requirements and to the possible
solutions because it's so much easier
for users to react to something that you
put in front of them instead of just
relying on this abstraction of
requirement statements or user stories
so i became a big fan of design modeling
and analysis modeling as well that was
another real turning point in my career
you asked about big changes and that was
another big one when i took a class on
structured systems analysis and design
and i realized wow before i sit down and
just start writing code
i can learn a great deal and think a
great deal and understand much better
if i draw pictures to represent my
proposed system or my problem at a
higher level of abstraction than just
writing code or writing text
and i found that extremely powerful so
i've been a big fan of modeling for a
long time because it's a lot easier to
change models it's a lot easier to
change prototypes than it is to change a
system you think you're done with
so how do you constantly design
something do you reach back to what
you've just said they're prototyping and
proving the idea well i wouldn't say you
constantly design it i would say you
repeatedly design it
and that is you take multiple attempts
to come up with a design that's
progressively better each time and then
you build from your best design i'll
give you an example i have a friend
who's a highly experienced designer
and he said you haven't done your design
job
if you haven't thought of at least three
solutions
discarded all of them because they
weren't good enough and then combined
the best parts of all of them into a
superior fourth solution
so what we don't want to do i think is
be designing continuously
while you're trying to to build the
application as well
and i think unfortunately that happens
sometimes people tend to not think of
design as a discrete
development stage a discrete thought
process
and people who are building systems
hastily in a rush to get them out like
maybe on some agile projects
they might skimp on design they build
something and it works and we say okay
but then they are having to constantly
redesign what they've done perhaps to
extend it to accommodate new
functionality and that's where you have
to do a lot of refactoring and that sort
of thing and architectural changes and i
don't think we should use that kind of
continuous design and redesign as a
substitute for doing some careful
thinking before you sit down to write a
lot of code
yeah there's a lot you can do up front
before you keep your fingers touch the
keyboard right and you're always going
to change because you're going to learn
new things and businesses change
approaches and technologies change so
you have to be able to adapt to that
but i don't think the idea of look well
we can build code really quickly we can
refactor it for the next iteration i
don't think that should be a substitute
for thinking
and um there must be a point where you
get so far along that you can change the
design how do you manage that well that
becomes very expensive right and a good
example of when that can happen is if
people have not done a
thoughtful job about exploring some
non-functional requirements
along with the functionality and that's
one of the tricky things about
requirements is that the part that
people naturally think of when you're
discussing requirements is the
functionality the behaviors the system's
going to exhibit under certain
conditions as you try to do things
but we also have
all kinds of non-functional requirements
a lot of which are in the category of
quality attributes the so-called ilities
right usability portability
maintainability
some of these are internal to the system
more important to developers maintainers
some of them are external and more
important to users like security and
availability
but if we don't make that an important
part
of our requirements exploration
then we can have a problem just like
you're getting at gavin because
some of those have pretty profound
implications for both functionality to
be added and architectural issues and if
you
don't think about for example certain
reliability things well in some kind of
products
where reliability is maybe critical you
may end up building it and saying oh
this does what we need but it crashes
too often i can't trust it to you know
do those communications as we need to
and re-architecting that can be pretty
expensive or sometimes maybe essentially
impossible that's where you get into
trouble so i think the non-functional
aspects of the system have to be
explored carefully along with the
functionality because you don't just
write down you know the system's
availability requirements on a story
card and then patch it in when you get
around to it that just doesn't work
thank you i'd like to move us on to
project management so in our journey
we've got the
chemical
tracking system tracking system yeah
sorry we've done enough user
requirements cases use cases up front to
get going we're potentially starting a
prototype and some design models that
we've maybe done three of and chucked
them out and started again
but we're on our way so we obviously
need to manage the project now so lesson
31 in your book talks about the project
team needs flexibility around at least
one of the five dimensions of scope
schedule budget staff and quality so i
guess that's the five things scope
schedule budget staff equality can you
take us through that
yeah this is uh kind of getting back to
an it's an extension of an idea that
most project managers are familiar with
they've heard of the classic iron
triangle
sometimes called the triple constraint
of project management
and the colloquial statement of that is
you know a sign you might see at a gas
station when you take your car in
what do you want good fast or cheap pick
two
you know the idea that you can't have
everything that you want necessarily
there's some competition some trade-offs
and the problem i had with that classic
iron iron triangle is that first i've
seen it drawn in multiple ways with
different labels on the vertices the
most common ones are time cost and scope
on the three vertices of the triangle
and we're all kind of familiar with
those trade-offs
sometimes quality shows up in the
triangle but sometimes it doesn't
sometimes it's sort of in the middle but
i don't know what that means does that
mean quality is a given so that all the
other parameters have to be adjusted to
get high quality maybe
or does it mean well you get whatever
quality you get within the constraints
that these other parameters impose
that's not clear so i was never
comfortable with that representation
and so i came up with this idea of these
five dimensions that you mentioned
scope
schedule
budget staff and quality sometimes
people put in risk but risk really isn't
adjustable in the same way these others
are and the fact is people do make
trade-offs with these against each other
including quality all the time
people might decide to ship a product
that they know is defective in some ways
with the idea rightly or wrongly
that from a business point of view it's
better to get the product out there fast
than it is to make sure that everything
works right although i don't think
customers always agree with that
attitude so i try to also split
resources that you see sometimes in that
iron triangle into budget and staff two
different aspects of resources i've
known of teams that had funding but they
had a head count limitation they
couldn't hire new people but they could
use that money in other ways maybe
outsourcing or buying a package solution
or something so the idea behind this
lesson is that there are these
trade-offs people have to make and
constraints they have to work within if
they want to be successful
would you say that those five things are
applicable to whether it's a business
application a hobbyist application or
you know because obviously if it's a
hobby one you might not want to spend
any money but the staff level is just
you the quality is as good as you want
to make it and the schedule is as quick
as you want to do it but right so that's
a little different
situation for most commercial or
business situations
but it still sounds like it's applicable
though i think it is
i can tell you kind of how this works
and why we need to do this analysis of
those different dimensions so i was
teaching a class on project management
once at a
state government agency and a woman in
the class after i talked about this
raised her hand she said all right so
here's our situation we've got a fixed
feature set that all has to be delivered
there can't be any defects we've got a
schedule and has to be done on time i
can't get more money the budget's fixed
and i can't get more people more staff
if i need them so what do i do
that means none of the fiber and the
gosh of all that
exactly right gavin that's exactly the
point and my point was is you will fail
because
if you don't have everything perfect
then you're going to have some
limitations here the first estimate that
turns out to be low someone who decides
to leave the company unexpectedly the
first time someone comes along and says
hey could you add this any of those
kinds of changes
you don't have any way to respond to
them you need some flexibility
around certain of those dimensions and
as you were alluding to a few minutes
ago depending on the nature of your
project
certain of those dimensions may not be
flexible you know they may be
constraints y2k projects were time
constrained right that had to be done on
a certain date and that's true of things
like okay the euro conversion brexit
all of those things had time constraints
so schedule was a constraint you didn't
have any choice
so that means something else has to be
flexible
so i think of a constraint as being a
dimension about which you have no
flexibility the project manager just has
to deal with that reality
the second category a
dimension could fall into is what i call
a driver
and a driver
is one of the major kind of success
objectives for the project which may
have a little bit of flexibility but
it's important to try to achieve that
and any dimension that's not a
constraint or not a driver
is a degree of freedom which has a
certain amount of adjustability to it
and the project manager needs to know
how much adjustability
so the trick
and this is the balancing point for any
kind of project is to do some analysis
so you understand what's critical what's
constrained is it schedule
is it quality you know for a life
critical system
you know you probably rather ship it a
month late if you have to to make sure
you don't kill somebody with it so the
project manager has to try to
achieve
the success drivers
by adjusting the degrees of freedom
within the limits imposed by the
constraints
so success could be we have to get it
delivered by you know the first of july
and then you've got you can negotiate
around the other four or you might say
we can't hire any more staff but we're
flexible on how much it costs or you
know those types of things right or
you've got to prioritize feature set so
that you can say well we've got to have
these basic features but beyond that
there's some flexibility and how many
more we can include
with our fixed team size and our fixed
schedule constraint so you have to know
which ones of those are adjustable for
and a good way to have that conversation
is suppose you're talking to a manager
customer project sponsor and they say
okay this has to be delivered by july
1st
well ask the question what happens if
it's not delivered by july 1st yeah i
was going to ask them who's dictating
that the customer the internal staff
right so challenge that you know or at
least inquire about it to understand i
mean you're not saying no you're saying
help me understand what happens if we're
not done by then and maybe the answer is
well we're going to get a fine of 20 000
euro a day because we're not in
compliance with some important
regulation well that's a pretty serious
consequence that sounds like a
constraint to me so july 1st it is but
what if the answer is well we'd like it
by july 1st you know to go along with
our other product launches
but you know if we didn't make it out
until the third week of july we can live
with that okay it's a success driver but
it's not a constraint so you need to
know which ones are adjustable and how
much
adjustment there is in there how much
flexibility so you can adapt to changing
realities
and hopefully some of this has been
caught in the requirements stage well i
think it's really part of the project
planning stage and you could understand
i think that from more from a business
point of view than from a specific
software or solution requirements point
of view from a business perspective
you'll know what's constrained if you're
working in a four-person company you're
going to be staff constrained you know
so that limits the size of things you
can do in a certain period of time so i
think that's more of a business
perspective than a application
or requirements perspective
is there a common theme you've seen in
your commercial training and consultancy
well it varies a lot i mean what
everybody really wants i think is they
would like an application that has all
the functionality anybody would ever
want with zero defects instantaneous
response time delivered tomorrow for
free i don't know how to do that
and so obviously we compromise in some
of those areas right and it's gonna vary
from situation to situation but one of
the common patterns that i think is one
to watch out for
is treating quality as a default
adjustable parameter in other words well
yeah it's got some bugs in it but it's
thursday and we said we were going to
ship it on thursday so we got to ship it
because we're done now it's thursday
and that i think is short-sighted partly
because you know customers don't like
bugs i remember reading a an interview
once with bill gates many years ago when
he was still at microsoft and the
interviewer asked well how do you
respond to the complaint from
users that microsoft software has a lot
of bugs and the answer was and i believe
this is a verbatim quote our users don't
care about bugs they care about features
i've never spoken to anyone who agrees
with that
so i think too often the default is well
the quality is whatever it is and we'll
answer the phone if it rings and i don't
really agree with that in every case but
there may be certain cases like if
you're trying to be first to market with
a highly innovative project
and your target market is early adopter
innovator people maybe that's okay so
it's a business decision
yeah i'm going to move us on to the next
session just so i can keep us on track
with time because i want to get a lot
covered with you but just to close off
that section in the network engineering
world the iron triangle which is the
first time i've heard of it but we call
it you make a choice between fast cheap
and reliable so if you're going to buy a
router or a router if you want it fast
and reliable it's not going to be cheap
so i just thought i'd chuck that in
there if we move on to culture and
teamwork so
knowledge is not
zero sum this is less than 35 in your
book and what ways can culture and
teamwork positively and negatively
impact a software project for example
the one we're talking about chemical
well this lesson gets to one of those
aspects of how culture and teamwork can
affect the project and let me tell you
what i mean when i talk about culture i
think a healthy software engineering
culture
is characterized by a set of shared
values and technical practices that lead
to constructive and congruent that's
important behaviors on the team
and i talk about this in my very first
book which was published back in 1996
and called creating a software
engineering culture and the willingness
to freely share knowledge among team
members and to comfortably seek
knowledge from your colleagues that's
one of those constructive behaviors i
had a great counter example of that that
helped bring this home i used to work
with a guy named ron
and ron was older than me he'd been
around a little longer at kodak
and so i would go ask ron a question and
i could almost see the wheels in his
brain working he'd be thinking well if i
give carl the whole answer to his
question he'll be as smart as me about
that i don't want that so i'm going to
give him half the answer and see if he
goes away
so then you come back for another half
of the answer and that's all you get you
want the rest of the answer you just get
another half so you asymptotically
approach getting an answer and i just
didn't appreciate that i think when
we're working together we should be
willing to share what we know with other
people and that positively affects a
team because we all do better when we
all know more and we all are willing to
ask for help or get somebody to look
over our shoulder at something
so i think that that's a real important
way to improve the culture as another
example in that creating a software
engineering culture book i described 14
principles that our small software team
in the kodak research labs had adopted
as shared values and one of them was
that we would rather have a co-worker
find a defect instead of having a
customer find a defect and as a result
we routinely practice technical peer
reviews of each other's work it was just
ingrained in our culture we rewarded
people who participated in the reviews
and who submitted their work to review
by their colleagues but we didn't punish
people based on how many defects we
found that would be a real culture
killer
now someone joined our group who didn't
want to participate in reviews for
whatever reason there's going to be a
culture clash and that just wouldn't be
the right place for them to work so i
think having those kinds of factors to
steer a culture in a collaborative
effective direction is really critical
and managers play a big role in shaping
that culture
by
helping to establish those principles
and values and by exhibiting behaviors
that are consistent with those have you
ever seen a case where management said
they valued one thing like quality but
then they rewarded different behaviors
like people who delivered on time
without necessarily delivering quality
and then people had to fix it never seen
that kind of incongruence
yeah and it depends two immediate
questions that spring to mind when you
talk about giving a colleague the full
answer and also peer review
obviously has to be encouraged and that
time needs to be there by the management
to allow you to do that but how do you
figure out whether they've put enough
effort in for you to justify giving them
a full answer rather than just trying to
get the answer out of you exactly now
that's a good question and i think
you do have to kind of judge are you
trying to get me to do your thinking for
you
or are you just relying on my experience
in this particular area so that i can
give you an answer faster than then you
might have dug it up on your own and
probably a better answer based on my
experience rather than just whatever you
found online
and i think that's a situational
judgment i think
in a software team or any team really we
all know who the top performers are
we all know who's coasting or struggling
or
maybe just trying to get other people to
do their work for them i don't think
that's a secret and if i was working in
a team and the same person kept coming
to me with what seemed like relatively
straightforward questions things they
should already know the answers to
things they should have been able to
look into themselves
that's a problem
but if i'm on the other hand people come
to me because i have certain expertise
that they don't have and i can impart
that thereby giving them some of that
expertise on their own which they now
own forever
we all win so it is a trade-off decision
but i think in each case you just have
to kind of assess the situation and see
which of those scenarios we're talking
about yeah you could always ask what
have you tried and then also judge well
if i spend a bit more time with you
right now hopefully that'll
self-empower you to do it yourself next
time right you're just kind of giving
them a start and appointment maybe the
help you provide is simply pointing them
towards resources and say look here's a
book i found really helpful or here's a
couple of articles i think i'll answer
your question why don't you check those
out and then come back if there's
something you don't understand so i
think we can handle that in an equitable
way without you know just ending up
doing everybody else's work because you
happen to know stuff
and you mention peer review and
preferring your colleagues to find
issues or bugs is that something that
you know you mentioned management do
they need to buy into that how do you do
that if if one of your constraints and
the five
constraints of scope schedule budget
staff and quality is schedule you know
where do you find that time to keep the
quality up ah you're raising a very very
interesting and important point here
gavin okay so let's say our constraint
is scheduled and what you're saying is
gee we've got a certain amount of time
you've got to get a certain amount of
work in
and you're saying if i maybe you're
thinking is well if uh if i'm on that
team and if i spend two hours reviewing
this person's code or requirements or
whatever then that's two hours i'm not
spending on my own project to get my
work done so i'm behind schedule
and the fact is that well-conducted
reviews almost always pay off more
than they cost
that is the time you spend collectively
on a review
finds enough defects early enough that
you can fix them quickly and cheaply
rather than having them get into the
final product and have the customer call
you later so that you come out ahead by
doing that now if reviews are not
effective
in terms of actually finding problems or
in that rare case where you don't have
any problems to be found
then that payoff doesn't come through
but my experience has been there's
almost always a high return on
investment from people once they get
into an effective review culture so
that's one way to think about it it's
not just what i pay today it's what i
reap
downstream by avoided rework
because of what i paid today the second
way to think about it is that whenever
you're asked to do something different
or extra your immediate reaction is to
think well what's in it for me but the
right way to think about it is what's in
it for us collectively and when you
start thinking that way you become more
willing i think to participate in
shared quality activities
and you could also be using that two
hour peer review and you're staring at a
bug that you're already working on you
know or you recognize something that
you're doing so you're actually working
on what you're supposed to be working on
by helping someone else at the same time
yeah i've learned something from every
review i've participated in and i don't
know about you but i've had the
experience where i'm staring at that bug
and i just can't see it and i ask
somebody hey jim can you come take a
look at this for me i just can't see
this and jim looks over your shoulder
and as you're explaining it to him one
of two things happened either you figure
it out while you're explaining it
or jim says i think maybe this comma is
in the wrong place oh that's it just
didn't see it have you had those kind of
experiences yeah sometimes you
think
what's in front of you and it's not
actually there you've switched that part
your brain off to say right i know
what's in that part of the project or
the code right you just need a little
help from your friends sometimes and
that's what you've done on
the rubber ducky technique and other
things like that cool right we've
touched on the next section which is
perfect which is called quality so
which ties us back into the peer review
bit that we've just had a little chat
about so less than 45 in your book
state when it comes to software quality
you can pay now or pay more later is
this really true how do you define
quality
well i think not only is there a lot of
data published to support that argument
that it costs you more to fix problems
later than earlier but it just seems
logical i mean the later in the
development process or let alone after
it's in production that you find a
problem the harder it is to debug it to
diagnose the failure and find the
underlying fault also the later you find
the problem the more components you
might have to modify to correct it you
know requirements designs code tests and
so on and you can get this big ripple
effect if you have this cascading series
of changes required maybe even in
multiple connected components or systems
so it stands to reason that if you could
find say a requirement or design error
before you've completed implementation
based on that
piece of knowledge it's going to cost
less to deal with it so we want to try
to find defects as close as possible to
the point in time at which they were
injected into the development process
and i think that's true regardless of
the development life cycle or
methodology that you're following it's
always going to cost more to fix it
later than earlier it's hard for me to
imagine how that could not be true
we need to define quality so we can test
it and prove that we've got quality
and that ties us back to the use cases
the requirements
how do we make sure that a use case is
of high quality so we can potentially
write our tests to prove that quality
maybe it's best explained with an
example that you've come across
well the whole definition of quality is
kind of a funny concept and when i was
writing this book i looked up some
definitions of software or generally
product quality and i found a lot of
different definitions they all had merit
but none of them were perfect or
comprehensive so i decided i wasn't
going to try to presume to solve that
problem and come up with a perfect
definition of software quality but i
learned two things from that one quality
has multiple aspects you don't just have
a you know 10 word definition of quality
that fits everything
second quality situational
so i guess we could probably all agree
that in the context of developed
software quality describes how well the
product does whatever it's supposed to
do and so instead of trying to find the
perfect definition i think it's
important for each project team to
explore what does quality mean to its
customers
how are we going to assess that
how are we going to achieve it and
communicate that to all the project
participants
you asked about examples and i think
it's easier to think of examples of poor
quality than good quality
so what's poor quality software mean to
us it might mean the products don't let
us do the things we need to do
it might mean it doesn't align well with
our business processes
and might mean that the products too
hard to use or it's full of defects and
crashes a lot it doesn't behave the way
you expect to and you get surprised by
what it does
for security holes there's a lot of ways
that you can encounter poor quality
just last week i installed the latest
windows 10 update on my on two of my pcs
well really microsoft automatically
installed those for me thank you very
much and both went to nearly 100 disk
activity all the time never had that
problem before i spent hours trying to
figure out what was going on and that
strikes me as a quality problem
somewhere
so i don't know about you but i
encounter products all the time that
appear to be designed by someone who
never used a product of that kind or has
some other deficiencies
and that's why i wrote my previous book
the thoughtless design of everyday
things
which you know shows a lot of the kinds
of places we can fall short on quality
even though i can't give you a nice
concise definition of it but i think
each team needs to think about it and
then figure out okay based on what we
think quality means today what are we
going to do to try to lay the foundation
for that and ascertain when we're there
yeah i think
i've got an example too where
quality could be
again what you've just said it depends
on what the requirement is what the
actual user thinks is important so a
product could get something done in half
an hour with no no errors is that
quality or they could get it done with f
within five minutes with 95 success you
know that yeah that might be good enough
but you don't know
exactly one that i found last week was a
accountancy software
application that we use online for years
and we switched our payment processors
so the screen hasn't you know the design
the layout of the page doesn't change
but the backend logic has obviously
changed because we're using a new credit
card provider but
it's as if they've never tested it with
someone sitting in front of it and i'm
thinking about the book that you just
said i've seen that book before and you
kind of gave me a copy where this is out
in public and nobody's actually sat down
put in their credit card details and
tried to put in a different billing
postcode or zip code like in america
it's using the default one on their
system
which might not be where the credit card
statement gets sent to you know it's
different i was like how could they even
done this and someone do that you know
and then support because it comes down
to the quality issue and i will deal
with that when it happens which no
customer agrees with no customer will
ever agree with that attitude but so i
have to open a ticket or log into the
system change their main contact address
because they want to pay for a credit
card which just you know reinforces
everything you've explained with those
lessons and basically your conclusion is
this is rubbish
right yeah somebody might even think
it's good quality
it's not good quality it's not good
quality and you know another place i've
encountered that is just in the course
of my daily life as you're sitting next
to someone on an airplane or talking to
the cashier in a store or talking to a
neighbor you would not believe how many
people have said to me once they learned
what i do for a living said well you
wouldn't believe this new system we have
to use at work i hate it they clearly
didn't talk to anybody like me before
they designed it and that's in the good
argument for usage-centered exploration
of requirements and designs and that's
what you've just said that is the same
thing that's happened for the past 50
years i know and that's the thing that's
so discouraging so i know a guy who was
one of he's the guy i consider the
father of requirements engineering and i
met him more than 20 years ago and he
told me at that time in fact it was
about 25 years ago i knew his work but i
met him and he said you know he stopped
teaching requirements classes because
after 20 years he was still saying the
same things to people to whom it was all
brand new
and he found that discouraging and i've
had the same kind of reaction because
i've been teaching requirements classes
now for about 25 years
and to me it's astonishing when i find
people that are professional business
analysts or developers or software
engineers
and i'm talking about stuff that's been
known for a long time
and they've never encountered it before
and they say wow what a cool idea
and that gets kind of discouraging so i
think there's not been nearly as much
progress in those aspects of software
engineering as there have in the more
technical aspects maybe because it's not
as much fun or it's not as cool but it
is a little discouraging to have all
this stuff still be fresh on the other
hand it does help keep books sort of
viable for many years
i've been doing programming
for
slightly over 20 years and you do see
the same
same things come and go that's why i
think software engineering and the show
in general is good because a lot of our
things are timeless okay i'm gonna move
us on to the last section of the show
because we're doing well on time anyway
i'm calling this process improvement
particularly your lesson 51 in your book
watch out for and quotes management by
business week what does that mean well
business week i think it's called
bloomberg business week now you know was
a magazine that what's going on in the
business world and technology worlds and
stuff and here's the scenario suppose
there's a senior manager for a software
organization and he's taking a flight or
you know just searching around and he
reads a magazine article or a blog post
or a news item
about some new software development or
project management methodology
it promises to bring great improvements
in productivity the manager thinks hey
terrific let's do that and all our
problems are solved so he goes back to
work and says we're all going to do this
new methodology because this is going to
make things lots better for us and that
is the manager decides to jump on the
bandwagon of whatever hot new approach
people are talking about and i think
that's a mistake so that's what i mean
by avoiding management by business week
i do that a devops email comes out on a
sunday and i always paste links into the
greek chat
yeah we should look at that yeah yeah
and sharing information is great but
here's what i think people ought to do
with that so
let's say it was devops okay i use in
the book i use a example of a
hypothetical method called method nine
you know as the example here oh that
sounds good let's get a twitter account
for that yeah yeah and that way we can
all be doing method nine because what
i've heard so far it sounds fabulous
right but here's what i recommend
whenever an organization wants to
achieve let's say better performance
however you define that productivity
whatever
i think what you should start with is by
asking yourselves why are we not already
achieving that better performance today
in other words do some root cause
analysis
of the issues that are preventing you
from being as successful as you'd like
to be
or understand the cause of some problem
and root cause analysis is a simple
technique that can really quickly and
efficiently help you identify the real
problem and from that you can identify
approaches to address those specific
causes that you think will lead to the
improvements and you might discover that
method 9 is not going to work because
that doesn't really address your root
causes no matter how good it sounded and
whatever you read maybe it doesn't help
you break down the barriers that are
preventing you from being as successful
as you want already so let's start with
some root cause analysis first
so how do you make time for that if you
have got a management instructor or a
manager
that always feeds you these new things
you know doesn't want to listen or
doesn't want to face the facts that
things are wrong is that an
organizational issue or what suggestions
you have for that type of scenario
well a couple of things sometimes it's
an educational thing i mean there's
nothing wrong with being ignorant we're
all ignorant about the vast majority of
knowledge in the universe being stupid
is another harder problem to deal with
but being ignorant it's okay it's a
matter of recognizing what you don't
know and being willing to learn it so
one thing that we have to do is manage
upward in a case like that and that's a
matter of of educating your managers
because sometimes the people who are
jumping on these bandwagons aren't
technical people they don't really
understand the barriers but if you're in
a position of being tasked to say go buy
method nine and we're gonna all you know
get trained and that's what we're gonna
do from now on
then i think your responsibility then is
to say well what is this going to do for
us and how do we know it's going to do
for us do that for us
in other words have we done an analysis
like a root cause analysis to figure out
what our current barriers are and be
confident that this is going to help
break them down maybe it will but let's
do the analysis first
i've never just done whatever my manager
told me to do i want to make sure i
understand what we're doing and
sometimes i will try to explain to them
why that is or isn't
the best thing to do and maybe you go
off and do a root cause analysis on your
own even and come back and say well we
thought about what you said and here's
what we learned are you sure this is
still what you want us to do you might
win you might not
well sounds like some good advice i've
got a couple more questions before we
start wrapping up if i squeeze them in
let's say let's just go back to our
project management section because i
really like the five dimensions of scope
schedule budget staff and quality if
we've got a struggling project so one of
those is way off or a couple of them
they're way off schedule or this got
massive scope creep or over budget are
there any quick wins that you could
recommend for a struggling project like
that well if there were quick wins that
would always work then i would sell them
and make a fortune and buy a very nice
house somewhere but i don't think
there's any magic solutions but i think
you do have to get back to understanding
why good example
scope creep is a perennial problem with
many software projects where new
functionality keeps coming along
and people keep finding well we've got
more to do than we thought we were going
to have to do and we're running out of
time but none of these other things have
changed you know we haven't got more
people we haven't got more money we
haven't got more time so how are we
supposed to make that happen well you
can't become more productive by decree
or by swapping out your whole team for
90th percentile people or something you
can't do that so i think you have to ask
yourself why are we experiencing this
phenomenon are we bad at estimating
did we not talk to the right users did
we overlook some key stakeholders and
all of us now we found them and their
needs are coming in very often when
you're getting a lot of ongoing scope
creep as opposed to just normal kind of
growth there's always growth and change
but if you find you've got an incessant
scope creep you're probably not doing a
very good job on requirements
elicitation
you're probably missing things maybe not
asking the right questions maybe
focusing on features instead of usage
maybe not doing a good job of
prioritization or maybe not doing a good
job of defining the scope of what you're
trying to do and then asking yourself
when each change comes along is this
really in scope you don't just throw it
on a story card and put it in your
backlog and without doing some filtering
first to see if it's the right thing to
do so again i think understanding why
we're experiencing that problem and how
that aligns with with your business
objectives helps you decide how do we
respond to that
well my last question i think you've
answered in that one would be what's the
most common issue you see and it sounds
to me like not doing the requirement
stage is a pretty big one well
yeah that's a big one but but you know i
used to uh years ago be involved with
some formal software process improvement
activities like with a capability
maturity model or cmm when that was a
big thing and i used to joke because one
of the things that was common with those
kinds of activities was to
do a formal process appraisal where
people would come in who were properly
trained and authorized and do an
appraisal of your organization to see
how well you were doing with respect to
the expectations of this improvement
model
and really kind of open the kimono and
see what was happening
and i used to kind of joke that i could
do
a process assessment for an organization
remotely for 100
i will send you a postcard and i will
write your top three problem areas on
that postcard and those areas would
always be requirements estimation and
testing
and those are the areas i think people
had the most difficulty with there are
others of course and this is you know a
little simplistic as a kind of a joke
but i suspect that those are still very
common issues that software teams
wrestle with i don't know what do you
see
or what are the kinds of things that
people encounter in your experience that
are chronic perennial challenges
i think it's pretty similar you know not
getting maybe too excited about the
project and cracking on too fast not
spending that time on the requirements
stage sacrificing testing
to just doing things in front of them
you know and not actually automating
those tests and using them as a safety
net pretty standard thing so you've
explained that you'd be shocked to not
think that they beat self by now right
and you know it's kind of funny there's
sort of an unstated mindset
among people who are eager i mean people
of course are eager to get into you know
writing code i mean that's what software
engineers like to do is build systems
and write code and all that but there's
sort of an unstated undercurrent here
that says we have to get started writing
code right away because it's going to
take us so long to fix it later well
maybe if we took an approach to think a
little bit more
and plan and explore
maybe you're not going to have to fix so
much of it later so not only is that
going to be cheaper but it's a lot less
stressful and you can probably
finish chunks of work quicker than you
thought because you're not devoting so
much of your effort to rework that's one
of my big bugaboos is rework i hate
rework i hate doing over something that
was already done now there's always some
of that for perfectly reasonable
legitimate reasons but i think if most
organizations took a look at
measuring how much of our total effort
is spent doing things over that maybe we
didn't have to do if we had taken a
different approach
sometimes you might find that you could
get a third of your
bandwidth back if you did take the time
to do some of these other things that
lay the foundation and iterate at the
higher levels of abstraction instead of
on releases and i think you'd probably
find that we come out ahead that way
most of the time but it's not as much
fun as writing code exactly obviously
it's very hard if not impossible to
distill 50 years of experience into one
book you've done a very good job let
alone one podcast episode but if there
was one thing a software engineer should
remember from our show what would you
like that to be
that's a good question i tried to in
this book to put in a lot of the things
i've learned from from a long time and i
guess one bottom line lesson is that i
have never known anyone who could
honestly say i am building software
today as well as software could ever be
built
and if you can't say that i think you
should always be looking for ways to
improve your processes and your
practices so the final lesson in the
book cautions you can't change
everything at once both individuals and
groups organizations can only absorb
change at a certain rate and still get
their project work done so you've asked
a couple of times
and how do you do this how do you get
time to do this in a busy project and
stuff and the answer is really you just
you have to make the time
to spend some of your effort on
improvement and growth and learning and
change and experimenting because
otherwise there's absolutely no reason
to expect the next project to go any
better than the last project and one of
the techniques that worked well for me
is that on every project i would try to
identify one or two areas i wanted to
get better at it could be estimation or
algorithm design or unit testing or
whatever
and i'd spend some of my time on that
project learning about those techniques
looking for opportunities to apply them
right away and you take a small
productivity hit every time you do that
it's a learning curve and that's there's
a price
but if i do that then in the process i'm
going to improve my own capability for
the rest of my career
so i encourage software engineers to
adopt some kind of systematic learning
philosophy always be carving out a
certain percentage of your project time
and managers too in the schedule
carve out a certain amount of time for
learning how to do the next project
better i think that's a real bottom line
message
thank you was there anything we missed
that you'd like me to ask or mention or
you'd like to mention now well maybe
just one point you know these are
lessons i've learned and i think you
shared some of those lessons or the
things there that you said yes i've
learned that or or no that doesn't apply
to me what was your reaction yeah my
career is
less than half of yours some things did
have
a common theme but other things were new
to me so
i think you know a lot of people should
spend more time reading all these books
there's so much out there and there's so
much knowledge that flash has passed us
there is so you've been around a while
you're not exactly a newbie and so
you've accumulated your own lessons
about how to do software development
more effectively and more efficiently
so i'm hoping that everybody would take
some time to think about their own
lessons
their own lessons to share those freely
with their colleagues like i alluded to
earlier
help the teams put those lessons into
practice and also be receptive to the
lessons that the people you work with
have also learned basically you don't
have time to make the same mistakes that
every software engineer before you has
already made and that's how i learned a
lot of these things is by doing
something that didn't go so well and
saying what should i do differently so i
think you can bypass a lot of these
painful learning curves or at least
flatten them out by absorbing knowledge
from people who have gone before which
is why i write books like this
excellent my two lessons i've learned
are it's always typos and it's always
permissions whether that's security
permission or you know business
permission so where can people find out
more obviously you're on linkedin which
i'll put a link into the show notes if
that's okay how can people get in touch
if they want to learn more about your
books your courses you know professional
consultancy that type of thing well my
company name is process impact and my
business website is processimpact.com
my personal website is not surprisingly
karlwegers.com
there are links at both of those sites
where people can send me messages and
there's also links from those pages to
the other pages or websites that
describe some of my books like software
development pearls the thoughtless
design of everyday things
successful business analysis consulting
and my forensic mystery novel that you
mentioned at the beginning the
reconstruction it's the only fiction
i've written and it was the most fun i
ever had writing i just had an
incredibly cool idea for a novel i said
yeah i wonder if i can write fiction and
other than my phd thesis long time ago i
hadn't written any fiction so i gave it
a shot and it was just a blast and had a
fun time doing that so those websites
are all accessible from
processimpact.com or karlwegers.com
plus of course you can hear the songs at
carlwegers.com if you dare
carl thank you for coming on the show
it's been a real pleasure this is gavin
henry for software engineering radio
thank you for
listening for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening